<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The house-holders helpe, for domesticall discipline: or A familiar conference of household instruction and correction fit for the godly gouernment of Christian families. Dedicated to all religious house-holders by R.R. minister of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>R. R., minister of Gods Word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841843</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6457</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 581:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The house-holders helpe, for domesticall discipline: or A familiar conference of household instruction and correction fit for the godly gouernment of Christian families. Dedicated to all religious house-holders by R.R. minister of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>R. R., minister of Gods Word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 37, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By George Purslowe, for Iohn Budge, and are to be solde at the great South dore of Paules, and at Brittaines Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.R. = Richard Rogers (?)--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:1"/>
            <p> THE Houſe-holders HELPE, For Domeſticall Diſcipline: OR</p>
            <p>A Familiar Conference of Houſe-hold inſtruction and correction, fit for the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gouernment of Chriſtian FAMILIES.</p>
            <p>Dedicated to all religious Houſe-holders by <hi>R. R.</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REVEL. 3. 19.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>As many as I loue, I rebuke and chasten: be zealous therefore and repent.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>George Purſlowe,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the great South dore of Paules, and at Brittaines Burſſe. 1615.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:2"/>
            <head>To all Religious houſe-holders, their Children and <hi>ſeruants: the ſauing knowledge</hi> of Gods holy Word, moſt <hi>heartily wiſhed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſt Chapter of the Prouerbs of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> it is written thus in the eight and ninth verſes: <hi>My ſon, heare the inſtruction of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forget not the lawe of thy mother: for they ſhall be an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of grace vnto thy head, and chaines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy necke.</hi> From which words may be drawne a double doctrine: Firſt, that all godly Parents ſhould teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their children in the Lawe of the LORD: Secondly, that their children
<pb facs="tcp:6457:3"/> ſhould learne &amp; obey their wholſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. For the firſt, wee haue both practice and precept therof in the ſacred Scriptures: the practice in <hi>Dauid;</hi> who <note place="margin">1 The prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their children.</note> taught <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne, ſaying, <hi>And thou, Salomon my ſonne, know thou the God of thy father, and ſerue him with a perfect heart, and with a willing minde,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. 9. <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo ſayth, that his father <hi>Dauid</hi> taught him and ſayd vnto him, <hi>Keepe my commandements and liue: Get wiſedome, get vnderstanding,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Prou.</hi> 4. 4. This was the practice, alwaies, not onely of godly fathers, but alſo of godly mothers: So did King <hi>Lemuels</hi> mother, ſhe taught her ſonne leſſons of chaſtitie, of temperance, of defending the afflicted, of chooſing, vſing, and commending a vertuous wife; as appeareth throughout the 31. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Prouerbes: and in this firſt Chapter thereof, in the eight and ninth verſes, <hi>Salomon</hi> preſuppoſeth that al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mothers will bee helpers to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, in the religious and godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction <note place="margin">2 Precepts of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it of Parents.</note> of their children.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee haue in the Scriptures plentifull ſtore of precepts, requiring
<pb facs="tcp:6457:3"/> this duty of all godly Parents: As <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6. 7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11. 19. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 78. 5. 6. <hi>Prou.</hi> 22. 6. In which place laſt mentioned, <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth: <hi>Teach a child in the way that he ſhould goe, and when hee is old, he will not depart from it.</hi> And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Fathers, prouoke not your children vnto wrath, but bring them vp in nurture and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, there are many reaſons and <note place="margin">3 Reaſons to perſwade Parents to performe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd duty.</note> motiues in the ſacred Scriptures, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all godly Parents to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this dutie: which I will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in another place more largely relate; meane time remember (O Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) and looke backe to <hi>Salomons</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue <note place="margin">1 By the practice thereof, they ſhall make them vertuous and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, adorn them and dignifie them; yea, inrich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> in this text, <hi>Prou.</hi> 1. 8. 9. to wit, that Parents ſhall (by the bleſſing of God) vpon their good inſtruction, make their children religious and vertuous, as God promiſeth, <hi>Prou.</hi> 22. 6. Yea, they ſhall thereby adorne them and dignifie them, inrich them, and make them <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> and <hi>gracious,</hi> both with God and men; vvhich <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo meaneth, when hee ſayth: that <hi>Their inſtructions ſhall bee an ornament of grace about their</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6457:4"/> 
               <hi>head, and chaines about their necke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe, doſt thou neglect this <note place="margin">2 By neglect of it, they make them moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, poore, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and odious, both to God and men.</note> dutie of inſtructing them: then doſt thou make them moſt miſerable, poore, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, naked and deformed: yea, moſt lothſome and odious both to God and men<hi>:</hi> as were the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> by their blindneſſe, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 17. &amp; 18. and <hi>Elye</hi> his ſonnes by their profaneneſſe, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 12. &amp; 17.</p>
            <p>Yea, aſſuredly, it may bee ſayd of thee, that through thy negligence, thou makeſt thy Children, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did the people; <hi>(Euen naked vnto their ſhame:) Exod.</hi> 32. 25. yea, and vnto thine owne ſhame and ruine for euer without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Remember <hi>Elyes</hi> downfall, and his ſonnes, though <hi>Ely</hi> were an elect; becauſe hee did not continually admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, and duely correct them: he admoniſhed them earneſtly for a fit, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 23. but not conſtantly, ſay ſome; neither did he correct and chaſtiſe them accordingly, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 13. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee haue neerer examples, euen at home; for if wee caſt our eyes vpon the World, wee may by dayly experience
<pb facs="tcp:6457:4"/> ſee, that ſuch Children as are left vnto themſelues without Diſcipline, they ſhame themſelues and their Parents, and liue in all outragious euils, in Swearing, Beſſelling, Whoring, Mocking, Lying, Murmuring, Sabbath-breaking, ſtealing; &amp;c. till at length they come to fearefull ends: accuſing then their Parents neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of diſcipline; who drew them to deſtruction, as the Dragon drew downe the Stars with his tayle, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12. 4.</p>
            <p>Remember (O Parents) that your <note place="margin">3 The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and equity of this duty, to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by Parents.</note> Children haue receiued corruption from you by naturall birth, and by conception: hauing therefore polluted them, you ſhould be carefull to purge them: they are conceiued, you know, in ſinne, and ſhapen in iniquitie, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. They are by naturall birth, as all others are, <hi>The Children of wrath and condemnation, Ephe.</hi> 2. 3. O therefore, let Chriſtian e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and pittie mooue you to vſe all good meanes, that they may bee gotten againe by the ſeede of regeneration, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. To which purpoſe, prepare them for the ſpirituall ſeede, by catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them, and when it is ſown in them,
<pb facs="tcp:6457:5"/> endeuour by dayly admonition, and good inſtruction, to harrow it and to roote it into their hearts: in ſo doing, <note place="margin">4 A farther inlarging of the vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; by ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome particulars of it.</note> whereas they are by naturall birth onely <hi>carnall, Ioh.</hi> 3. 6. and fleſhly, hauing not the Spirit, <hi>Iude</hi> 5. 19. and ſo doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble Sathan, and are his Image, you ſhall cauſe them to become ſpirituall, and ſo to reſemble God himſelfe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 24. and to become the <hi>Image of God, Coloſ.</hi> 3. 8. 9. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. 23. 24.</p>
            <p>That ſeede of <hi>Regeneration</hi> ſowne in their ſoules, wil keepe and preſerue them from the dominion and power of ſinne, ſo that they ſhall not ſinne as do others, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 6. and <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 2. nor as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and his ſonnes doe ſinne in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe, nor to condemnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 1. becauſe <hi>Gods ſeede remaineth in them,</hi> and becauſe they <hi>are borne of GOD,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 8. 9.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, by that ſeede of <hi>Regeneration</hi> once receiued, they are made <hi>Immortall,</hi> as the ſeede it ſelfe is; which is therefore called <hi>Immortall</hi> ſeede, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 23. 24. 25. becauſe it makes them <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> and to liue for euer which doe
<pb facs="tcp:6457:5"/> receiue it, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> ſpeaking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſuch as were to teach his ſonne, ſayd, that hee himſelfe being a <hi>Mortall</hi> man, had made his ſonne <hi>Mortall</hi> by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; but yet he hoped that his tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers by good inſtruction, would make him <hi>Immortall.</hi> So may wee ſay of our ſonnes and daughters; that by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wee haue made them <hi>Mortall,</hi> euen ſubiect to a double death: yet may wee comfort our ſelues in this, that by <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian inſtruction wee may make them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Immortall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See then by this, and conſider (O <note place="margin">5 A Corola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> Chriſtian Parents,) what ſpeciall priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and dignities you may procure for your Children by Chriſtian inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; thereby you may inrich them and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne them with all generall ſauing gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and with outward wealth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; in particular, you may make them of carnall, to become ſpirituall; of being Sathans Image, to become Gods owne Image; and of <hi>Mortall</hi> to become <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall,</hi> and to liue for euer.</p>
            <p>But what courſe muſt I take (wil ſome <note place="margin">6 Queſtions and Obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. 1. Queſtion Anſwere.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6457:6"/> ſay) with my Children, when they are well inſtructed in the principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? I anſwere, that after they haue beene fed with milke, they muſt be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and fed with meate: when they haue attained knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then their affections muſt bee much moued and wrought vpon, by the word of admonition, reprehenſions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, &amp;c. otherwiſe they will bee hardened by the cuſtome and deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 13. you ſhould therfore dayly admoniſh them, as <hi>Iob</hi> did his ſons, <hi>Iob</hi> 1. 5. without which courſe taken with them, the word preached will not worke vpon them ſo effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as otherwiſe by that meanes it might.</p>
            <p>I know no cauſe, nor need, ſay ſome, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> to admoniſh my children for any groſſe ſinne. No more, may I ſay, did <hi>Iob:</hi> yet <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> in a godly ielouſie did he oft-times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh his ſonnes, thinking, it may bee they haue ſinned; (though not in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward behauiour, yet in their hearts) by blaſpheming GOD in their hearts, <hi>Ib. Iob.</hi> 1. 5. For as <hi>Iob</hi> alwaies feared euen his beſt works; which who ſo doth not,
<pb facs="tcp:6457:6"/> cannot be be bleſſed, <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 14. ſo he conſidered that mans heart is a ſinke and ſea of all iniquitie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 19. and therefore hee ſaith, that man <hi>Is abominable and filthie, and drinketh iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie like water, Iob</hi> 15. 16.</p>
            <p>You ſay, you ſee in them the true <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> works of regeneration: they are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, they cannot therfore ſinne, inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. True; yet they cannot but ſinne by <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> infirmitie, and euen haply ſometimes preſumptuouſly, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did: yea, if they be not oft-times admoniſhed, they cannot diſcerne the greatnes and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſnes of their groſſeſt ſinnes: for as the cuſtome and deceitfulneſſe of ſin harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſo it alſo blindfoldeth, as in <hi>Dauids</hi> example you may perceiue, who, till hee was reproued by <hi>Nathan,</hi> did not effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually repent, becauſe hee conſidered not, nor ſaw not the greatneſſe and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſnes of his ſinne, but by meanes of admonition, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 13. Hence is it, that th' Apoſtle willeth vs to rebuke the works of darkeneſſe: ſo calling them, becauſe they darken our vnderſtanding, and compareth the light of reproofe and
<pb facs="tcp:6457:7"/> admonition, to the light of a Candle, becauſe it diſcouereth our ſinnes that were hid vnto vs without it, as the light of a Candle doth the things which wee cannot without it eſpie and ſee, <hi>Epheſi.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
            <p>They are, you ſay, Gods image, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with true righteouſnes and holineſſe: yea they are vndefiled, <hi>Can.</hi> 5. 2. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot, vnblemiſhed, not to be blamed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 27. I anſwere, that Chriſtians are perfectly pure, by the puritie of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, by Chriſts righteouſneſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted; but not by the puritie of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or by righteouſnes renued: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the latter puritie, wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded continually to purge our ſelues from all filthineſſe of fleſh and Spirit, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. They are Gods Image alſo, by true righteouſneſſe renued, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 23. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 553 Imago De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i, ſicut eſt abolita corruptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſic eſt obſcurata fumo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum.</note> 24. Take heede therefore, that Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage be kept vndefiled, and as much as in you lyeth, vnſpotted of the world, <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 27. <hi>The Image of God in vs, is much defiled by vs:</hi> it is daily obſcured by <hi>the fume and ſmoke of our offences;</hi> (ſayth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Manuel:) Wherefore, you
<pb facs="tcp:6457:7"/> ſhould often ſet before you &amp; yours, the looking-glaſſe of Gods Law, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by beholding, both inward and outward blemiſhes, daily receiued by the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of ſinne; you and they may bee moued and directed, how to waſh them away by repentance. Who would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure his owne, or his friends Image or picture to be polluted, or his owne appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, or his face or hands, to bee ſtained; and would not often haue them purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and preſerued from pollution? And ſhall wee careleſly ſuffer the polluting and defiling of ſo great and worthy a Iewell as <hi>Gods Image is?</hi> See the danger of it, conſider it<hi>: If any man defile the ſame, him ſhall God deſtroy, Gen.</hi> 38. 10. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 10. <hi>Num.</hi> 25. 9. But now <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> to grow to an end: a queſtion heere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine may be moued; namely, whether Maſters are as carefully to teach and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their ſeruants, as their ſons? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere, that they are: for a houſe-holder <note place="margin">Why ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſhould bee catechized as well as ſons and children.</note> ſhould haue a fatherly care of his ſeruants, as if they were his ſonnes or Children, and is not to vſe them as they vſe their beaſts, reſpecting onely their
<pb facs="tcp:6457:8"/> labour, and the feeding of their bodies, as many Maſters doe: <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe family conſiſteth as well of ſeruants as of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſonnes, circumciſed his whole Familie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 13. and charged his whole houſhold to doe Iuſtice and Iudgement, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. If ſuch as prouide not for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> their Family bodily foode, as well for ſeruants as others, bee worſe then Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, as th' Apoſtle ſaith they are, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 8. then they muſt needs be much more worſe then Infidels, which prouide not ſpirituall foode for them. But what, are not thy ſeruants thy brethren in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Lord? And haue they not Soules to bee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fed and ſaued, as well as others? did not GOD ordaine the Sabbath, as well for inſtruction of ſeruants as ſonnes? <hi>Exod.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 20. 10. If by good inſtruction and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> thou purge not their ſpirituall pollutions, thou neglecteſt Gods Image in them, and they muſt needs infect thy Familie, and other Families: they will ſerue thee with eye ſeruice, vnleſſe thou make them, as much as in thee lyeth, to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> ſerue the Lord Chriſt: Then in ſeruing Chriſt truely, they will ſerue thee faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:6457:8"/> doing, as he ſaith; <hi>The will of God from the heart, with good will doing ſeruice vnto thee, as to the Lord, Epheſi.</hi> 6. 6. 7. 8.</p>
            <p>Theſe motiues therefore, let them be <note place="margin">7 A finall concluſion from the end and vſe of all the former Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> well meditated and pondered, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents may be ſtirred vp thereby to cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize and inſtruct their Children, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their welfare and their owne: Secondly, let Children bee willing for their owne credit and profit to heare and obey their Parents inſtructions: Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let Maſters for the like reſpect of Gods Commandement, and their owne commoditie, in making them to ſerue themſelues in the LORD; be diligent to catechize, inſtruct, and admoniſh them, accordingly.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:9"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:9"/>
            <head>THE Houſe-holders Helpe, FOR Domeſticall Diſcipline: OR A familiar conference concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſtian inſtruction, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, fit for Godly Families.</head>
            <div n="1" type="conference">
               <head>The firſt conference betwixt a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Gentleman, and his eldeſt ſonne and heyre, concerning houſe-hold inſtruction omitted.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Onne, I haue ſent for you, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſent for his ſonnes: who, though his ſonnes dwelt apart
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6457:10"/> from him, and had houſes, and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of their owne: yet hee ſent and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them home to his houſe, to giue them needfull <note n="a" place="margin">Fathers are to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thogh they dwell apart from them, and haue Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of their owne.</note> admonition. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. 4. &amp; 5. <hi>Verſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GOod Father, I thanke GOD for that your Chriſtian care of me, and according to my dutie, I will be willing and glad to receiue any good inſtruction from you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Deſire to haue ſome religious confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with you, and to admoniſh you, concerning <note n="b" place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect or mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall Diſcipline.</note> domeſticall Diſcipline; For I haue heard that your Familie is not <note n="c" place="margin">The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference.</note> catechized, admoniſhed, nor cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, according as formerly it was wont to be, by your wife, when you are from home; and which more is, I heare that your ſelfe doe oft-times fayle in the foreſayd duties, when you are at home; Is it ſo, my Sonne, is it ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6457:10"/>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GOod Father, with ſhame, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for it, I doe confeſſe it, to bee ſo: wee are much ſubiect to Spirituall i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe, and to Worldly carefulneſſe; I pray God giue vs pardon of, and power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe ſinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am ſorte, my Sonne, I am very ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for <note n="d" place="margin">Parents ſhould bee greeued at their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe, and pray for their reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> you; I pray God forgiue you, and amend theſe euill manners in you: I perceiue, by your teares, and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that you are humble-minded; and you do well to confeſſe your ſinnes, and to craue pardon of them, and power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; <note n="e" place="margin">Wee ſhould prayas ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin, as for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 13. And as Chriſt directs vs all to doe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 12. 13. Conſider alſo, my ſonne, that vnleſſe you do as well forſake your ſinnes, as confeſſe your ſinnes; you haue no promiſe of the pardon of them, <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 13. 14. <hi>Eſay</hi> 55. 7. nay, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is denied to them that go <hi>on in their</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:6457:11"/> 
                     <hi>ſinnes,</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin is deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them which con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue in ſinne: and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</note> 
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 21. in which places, you may alſo ſee, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auoidable deſtruction ſhall ſeize vpon all ſuch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O My Father, my hearts deſire is, not to loue ſinne, nor to liue in ſinne, but to loath and to leaue all ſinne; ſhew mee, (I beſeech you) by what meanes I may ſubdue and ouermaſter theſe my predominant ſinnes; theſe ſo ſtrong and mighty gyants.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>IF you deſire to ouercome theſe ſtrong corruptions, theſe mighty Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <note n="g" place="margin">The meanes to ouercome our ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and our predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſins.</note> you muſt be ſtrong in the Lord, <hi>and in the power of his might,</hi> wreſtle ſtoutly, and conſtantly encounter with them, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 10. you haue hitherto let the ſpirituall ſword too much ruſt in the ſheath: if you had often drawne that ſpirituall ſword, and ſkilfully with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and conſtancy reſiſted Sathan with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6457:11"/> it, as you are willed, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>&amp;c. &amp; verſe</hi> 16. 17. 18. Sathan would haue fled, as God hath promiſed, <hi>Iames</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 16. and as Chriſt for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and direction hath ſhewed, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 4. 11.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore you muſt bee better armed with more courage and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy againſt the next encounter; meane time you muſt iudge your ſelfe, that you may <note n="h" place="margin">The meanes to preuent fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is to iudge our ſelues before they come.</note> preuent future iudgments, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 31.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVHat (I pray you) is it, and how are we to endeuour it, to iudge our ſelues aright?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>AS a temporall Iudge doth firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the malefactors, and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils done, what, how many, how great, &amp;c. and then proceeds to puniſh; ſo muſt wee in iudging our ſelues; <note n="i" place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of iudging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</note> firſt exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our ſelues, what, how many, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6457:12"/> how great euils wee haue committed: next, wee muſt proceede to a ſpirituall iudgment, cenſure, &amp; puniſhment, by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigning our Soules and Spirits, with indignation inditing them of high trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and rebellion againſt GOD, at the Tribunall ſeate of God: Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wee muſt put vp ſupplication with ſtrong cries, in the name of Chriſt, for pardon of ſinne paſt, and power againſt ſinne to come. Fourthly, wee muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> curbe and correct our ſelues, euen cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, and externally; taking reuenge of our ſelues for our former faults, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 12. by watchings, faſtings, and by reſtraining our ſelues from many lawfull delights, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 16. Fiftly, wee muſt croſſe our corrupt courſes by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> contrary courſes oppoſite to our former vices, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 24. for as the rule is: <hi>Contraria contrarijs curantur.</hi> Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are cured by their contraries. And laſtly, if afterwards all theſe meanes being vſed, you be againe and againe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with theſe corruptions: yet ceaſe not to encounter; bid battell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vnto them, and with greater force
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6457:12"/> afreſh reſiſt them; conſidering that true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> haue alwaies crucified the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24. and doe dayly mortifie their earthly members, in regard of that glorious life that they looke for, <hi>Col.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Bernard, Si labor te<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terret, mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces inuitet.</note> 3. 4. 5. <hi>Iob.</hi> 31. 2.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DEare Father, this your counſell and comfort is as ſweetneſſe to my Soule, and as healing to the bones that are broken, Pro.</hi> 16. 24.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>GIue eare then againe, and I will yet go on in this argument, of iudging, puniſhing, and correcting your ſelfe; vpon often relapſe and falles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one and the ſame offence, (which if you doe) you ſhall preuent both tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eternall iudgements of ſinne, and in time ouercome the ſinne it ſelfe; of what ſort, or how great ſoeuer, the ſinne bee, with which you are <note n="l" place="margin">The vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues.</note> in war.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6457:13"/>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O But yet, ſome ſinnes are much more ſtronger then that I can (weake wretch that I am) euer bee able to ouercome them: of which ſort are thoſe, (I feare me) aforementioned.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>O Nay, ſay not ſo, my Sonne; haue you euer aforetime ouercome leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſinnes? yea, I doe know you haue; you ſay you haue ouercome raſh anger, ſwearing, &amp;c. why then, marke what comfort from thence you may conceiue vnto your Soule: <note n="m" place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to encounter with our ſtrongeſt corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> hee that can ouer-uercome raſh anger, wrath, pride, luſt, or any other like, <hi>Is ſtronger then hee that ouercomes a Citie, Pro.</hi> 16. 23. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> doth affirme that the toung is an vnruly member, and no man can tame it, <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 8. It is the onely grace and gift of God to tame it, which whoſo hath, not ſinning as before in word, hee is a perfect man, and able alſo to bridle
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6457:13"/> all the bodie, <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 2.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SIr, I remember wel that auncient rule in religion;</hi> 
                     <note n="n" place="margin">An anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent rule in Religion, (viz.) that the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and death of any one ſin, is the death in time of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery other ſin.</note> 
                     <hi>that the weakening, wounding, &amp; death of any one ſin, is the weakning, wounding, &amp; death in time of euery other ſin: and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth, that All that is borne of God, ouercommeth the world, and that this great victory is attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by faith,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 4. 5. <hi>Lord there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I pray thee, confirme and increaſe my faith, Luke</hi> 17. 5. <hi>O my good God, giue vnto me the ſhield of faith, wherwithall I may quench all the fiery darts of the diuell.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 16</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>YOu ſay well, concerning that rule; and it doth me good at my heart, that you collect the ſame in ſenſe from ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and conclude thereupon ſo well with earneſt prayer: I will therefore in concluſion of this counſell, encourage you by ſome examples of ſuch as by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſing and correcting themſelues, haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6457:14"/> ouercome moſt ſtrong corruptions: <note n="o" place="margin">Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſuch, as by chaſtiſing and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, haue by denying themſelues ouercome themſelues that is, the ſtrongeſt corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their fleſh: or their ſtrongeſt naturall, &amp; occaſional corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> 
                     <hi>Hemingius</hi> on the 15. Pſalm ſheweth; that he being at <hi>Witenberge,</hi> there came thither to hoſtage, a man exiled and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for the profeſſion of the Goſpell: this man, when he did oft times ſweare, through an euill cuſtome, and did at length conſider with himſelfe, how hée might amend this euil cuſtome; he came to D. <hi>Luther,</hi> and requeſted his counſel, how hee might by ſome meanes correct that cuſtome and abuſe of ſwearing. To whom, D. <note n="p" place="margin">Luthers counſell.</note> 
                     <hi>Luther</hi> giues counſell, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Command (ſayth he) thy wife, thy children, and the reſt of thy family, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a great penalty, to admoniſh thée of thy fault, as oft as they heare thee ſweare, and that ſtraiteway thereupon, they require of thee a great forfeiture of excellent gold. The honeſt Gueſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth and followeth <hi>Luthers</hi> counſell: he ſware, as before he was wont, hee is thereupon admoniſhed, and payeth for euery oath he ſweareth, much, and very good gold: but after a while, vpon much payment, hee happily, at length left this cuſtome of ſwearing; ſo that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6457:14"/> he was neuer heard to ſweare at all.</p>
                  <p>Other ſuch like examples <hi>Heminge</hi> in Latine ſheweth vpon the foreſayd Pſalme. <note n="q" place="margin">Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes counſell.</note> 
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> alſo giueth counſell in like caſe, to appoint a penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of refrayning ſome dinner, or ſome ſupper.</p>
                  <p>And another learned Authour coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth ſuch Houſeholders as know their owne proneneſſe, to fall oft in the ſame offence, whatſoeuer open ſin it be, to determine with themſelues; yea, to reſolue and vowe, that as oft as they fal againe into the ſame offence, to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen confeſſion to the family of the firſt offence, if the fault be knowne to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: for the ſecond fault to vſe abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and to eate but onely bread, and to drinke water onely for one or two meales: For the third fault, to refraine all ordinary food for one or two meales, and to giue it to the needy and hungrie: For the fourth fault, to forfeit and to giue away much money to many poore and <note n="r" place="margin">The cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and of very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</note> needy men.</p>
                  <p>Such examples are ſeldome ſhewed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6457:15"/> nor found in families: <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>Three exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced by the Authour of this Dialogue; yet ſuch exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are very ſeldome to be ſeene: howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it without this care of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelues, wee cannot preuent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 31. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed effectually. Herehence it is, that many of Gods deare Children, not vſing conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably and diligently, as well theſe as other ordinances of God, are ſo often ouercome by ſome grieuous corruptions, as were the Diſciples and the Corinthians, Matthew</hi> 18. 1 <hi>&amp;c. Luke</hi> 22. 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> Howbeit I haue ſeene onely three ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which I will preſcribe for pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes. The firſt was a verie reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious man, who in the hearing of all his family confeſſed his fault, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: I haue forgotten one maine and moſt principle doctrine, this Sabboth day deliuered, which I intended to haue repeated, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and applied to mine owne vſe and all yours: and therefore I am verily greeued at my owne forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: I will aſſuredly thus, and thus, chaſtiſe, iudge and correct my owne fault.</p>
                  <p>Againe, I haue ſeene a ſecond example hereof ſhewed by an honeſt hearted houſeholder, who vpon ſome open ſhewe of diſcord betwixt his wife and him, before the family, was preſently humbled for it, confeſſed it,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6457:15"/> &amp;c. And compared himſelfe &amp; his wife, to the couple peeces of the houſe, which if they fall aſunder, they cauſe other timber of the houſe to ſhrinke and to go out of order: ſo we, ſayth he, hauing fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len at variance, and openly reproued one another, (which reproofe ſhould haue beene in priuate) haue cauſed all the family to go out of order, and to imitate (as they are apt to do) our euil example: and thereupon will the leſſe reuerence our counſels, our perſons or reproofes hereafter: we will therefore (ſay they) confeſſe our faults, &amp; chaſtiſe our ſelues &amp;c. that thereby we may remoue theſe ſtumbling blocks from our familie, and learne to wax wiſer hereafter.</p>
                  <p>A third example, an other time I ſaw, <note n="t" place="margin">Third example ſeene.</note> when the Heads and Rulers of a Religious family had heard a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the Sabboth, and had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a good monition from the Miniſter their Preacher: namely, that Maſters and Miſtreſſes muſt not bée like <hi>Nabal,</hi> froward, and angrie; for anger reſteth in the boſome of fooles, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 7. 11. and great frowardneſſe is a note of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6457:16"/> great wickedneſſe and fooliſhnes, as <hi>Nabals</hi> example ſheweth, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 17. Afterwards they repeated the principall doctrines, which before were taught them in the Church, the which being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the humbling of their owne hearts, before in hearing, and then more particularly in repeating: they confeſſed themſelues before al the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue beene in time paſt very foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; for by frowardnes and continuall correcting, chiding &amp; threatning, which the Apoſtle wils Maſters to put away, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 9. they ſaw they had exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and hardned the hearts of their ſons and ſeruants, made them more froward, and prouoked them to wrath, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 4. and cauſed ſeruants to counterfait that, which they ſhould not, <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 9. for as they had heard from the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers mouth, that day, ſuch as are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies chiding, threatning, or correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are as little feared as the thunder would bee feared, if it did dayly thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. <note n="u" place="margin">The fruit of this laſt example.</note> This their foreſayd confeſſion wrought in them ſuch a change, &amp; a renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conuerſion, that they vowed as they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6457:16"/> were taught &amp; directed to do: To winke at and paſſe by many faults; either not <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 4 <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19. 11.</note> reprouing but ſeldome, or elſe not ſo ſharpely, but more mildly reprouing, and correcting with leſſe ſeuerity. Thus afterwards they became <hi>Lambs,</hi> which before were <hi>Lyons,</hi> through the power of Preaching, as the Prophet propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſhould be perfourmed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 11. 6. 7. 8. 9. This cauſed their Children and ſeruants, (they ſeeing them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and correct themſelues, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their manners,) to beare all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes and corrections with more humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, yea, both to be ready without gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying to yeeld, confeſſe, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a fault committed, with méeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and amendment euer afterwards. <note n="*" place="margin">The ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall end and vſe of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</note> By all this that you haue heard, you may euidently ſée the dignitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of this domeſticall Diſcipline, which ſhould firſt be impoſed by Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders vpon their owne ſhoulders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be layd vpon their ſeruants.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:6457:17"/>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Pray you (good Father) goe on yet a little farther, and as you haue ſhewed good generall remedies, ſo I humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to apply to my ſores ſome more ſpeciall ſalues, and coraſiues to mine</hi> 
                     <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>A good hearted hearer of Gods word is glad of ſharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 25. <hi>and deſireth to be ſmitten as Dauid did, knowing that to bee the onely way to bring ſolide comfort and health to ſoule and body: But on the contrarywiſe health is far from the vngodly, becauſe they regard not Gods ſtatutes, ſayth the Pſalmographe, and they hate to be reproued, Pſal.</hi> 50. 17. <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. 22. 1. <hi>Theſſa.</hi> 4. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>SIth I ſée you ſo willing to haue your ſores throughly ſearched into, and throughly healed; in particular there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for ſpirituall idleneſſe and ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſſe, to ſalue that ſore, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how Gods owne hand doth diſcouer the foreſayd ſore, and firſt, how hée bids vs to beware of ſo great a harme and hurt to our ſoules, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 9. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6457:17"/> 3. 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 11. 2. <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 8. <hi>Prou.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Math.</hi> 20. 6.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, conſider more ſpecially the euill effects thereof, ſpirituall idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is checked and blamed, mocked and ſhamed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <note n="y" place="margin">Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or motiues againſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> Checked by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. 6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Diſgraced by <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19. 24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It bringeth beggery, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pouertie ſpéedily, which we can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, reſiſt nor eaſily afterwards ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, <hi>Prou.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. An idle perſon ſhall haue Gods li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery and his badge pulled off from his backe, ſent out of Gods houſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice with ſhame: hee ſhall bée without ſpéedie repentance afterwards at laſt, perpetually impriſoned, <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 28.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, conſider <note n="z" place="margin">A ſpecial comfort applied to the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</note> that they which by idleneſſe are brought to ſuch extreame pouertie, that they are vtterly vnappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, and vnmonyed, as were the <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans, Reuel.</hi> 3. 17. 18. yet they are called and counſelled to come to Chriſt, who if they come humbly and faithfully
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6457:18"/> vnto him, will adorne them with royall robes, and enrich them with all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all treaſures, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 17. 18. as in the foreſayd place he promiſeth.</p>
                  <p>Now next I come to cure the ſecond ſore: <note n="*" place="margin">The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes, a ſore very hardly healed, yet a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagion, a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, &amp; deadly diſeaſe.</note> which is worldlineſſe and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, in which conſider. Firſt, that by couetouſnes we are made ſlaues and ſeruants vnto riches, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 13. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by couetouſneſſe wee commit ſpirituall whoredome againſt God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the world our god. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5. Thirdly, by worldlineſſe, wee choke the growth of the Word of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 14. Fourthly, by couetouſneſſe al euils are occaſioned: for, it is <hi>the root of all euill,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10. Fiftly, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate oft, and conſider the end wherfore God giues vs much goods, and riches: They are (ſayth one) <hi>Gods wages</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <note place="margin">Note.</note> he binds vs to obey &amp; do his work. When God giues vs wages to ſerue him, ſhall wée ſerue the world, Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy? <hi>We cannot ſerue God &amp; Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Luke</hi> 16. 13. Now, that riches are Gods wages, to occaſion vs to feare to offend GOD our maſter the giuer of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6457:18"/> them, it may bée plainely proued from Satans owne confeſſion, <hi>Iob</hi> 1. 9. 10. And from <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 47. From which laſt place, wée alſo learne, that when <note place="margin">Note and mark this well.</note> Gods worke is leſſened by vs, Gods wages ſhall bée leſſened to vs: yea, if for plenty, wee ſerue him not with ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity and chéerefulneſſe, wée ſhall haue worldly wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in place of worldly welth. And ſo much (I hope) ſhal ſuffice, for the ſaluing and healing of that other ſore, of worldlineſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HEale my ſoule, O Lord, for I haue ſinned againſt thee: Heale mee</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">A Prayer.</note> 
                     <hi>ſoundly with theſe thy ſalues applyed to mee. Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conference">
               <pb facs="tcp:6457:19"/>
               <head>The ſecond Conference, concerning Houſehold inſtruction to <hi>bee renued.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>OVr laſt conference was, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Houſehold inſtruction o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: <note n="a" place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect or mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of this ſecond confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> our next ſhall be now, how the ſame ſhould be renued. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you haue no publike catechizing, wée will firſt conſult what order &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of catechiſing is fitteſt for your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, on the Wéek daies, and then what inſtruction is moſt meet for them on the Sabbaoth dayes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WEe haue indeede no publike Catechizing in our Church to be followed and exerciſed in our houſes: otherwiſe, I ſuppoſe you</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6457:19"/> 
                     <hi>would wiſh vs to vſe the ſame in our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>YEs, ſo I would doe, in that caſe: but it being not ſo, I would haue you to vſe a certaine Catechiſme, commonly printed: called, <note n="b" place="margin">I doe not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but only commend it for the breuity and addition of ſome need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things, which larger Catechiſmes haue not, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Maſter Nowels, Perkins, and Pagets Catechiſmes are very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in many things: Yet no one man hath all things.</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſoles</hi> Catechiſme, which hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things needful, which other haue not: as firſt, the difference of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and actuall ſins: alſo, rules for the true vnderſtanding of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and the Sacraments, which no other briefe Catechiſme hath hitherto preſcribed: it is a very pithie and an excellent Catechiſme. Now, to preſcribe an order &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vſing it: After your Sonnes and ſeruants haue learned by the booke the meaning of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, then teach them the ſenſe, by vſe and experience: for all arts and tongues are better taught (you know) and learned by vſe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6457:20"/> then by rule and precept onely: and ſo are alſo the grounds of Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EXplane your meaning (I pray you) by ſome example.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Would wiſh, I ſay, after the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Commandements lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the booke, that you would teach the vnderſtanding of each Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, by vſe and experience: <note n="c" place="margin">Marke this and continue this courſe this order and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing.</note> As namely, by daily occaſion thus: When any in your family ſhal deceiue, lye, ſweare, murmure, curſe, mocke, raile, &amp;c. then preſently thereupon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſhew them by the book, what Commandement they breake: and when any duty to God or men is omitted, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and ſhew them by the book, what precept they offend againſt, teaching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to expreſſe the ſenſe in other words, that you may know they vnderſtand the meaning; and teaching them not onely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6457:20"/> by the booke, but alſo by liuely voyce and ſpéech. Thus to teach them, (I ſay) vpon occaſion, the vſe and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of that they haue learned, will, as I haue by tryall perceiued, both helpe their capacitie, confirme their memorie, and worke vpon their affections, the more effectually.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AFter this courſe of catechizing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued daily in the Weeke dayes, what other order of inſtruction would you wiſh chiefely to be continued vpon the Sabbath day?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Would wiſh you alwaies vpon the Lords day <note n="d" place="margin">Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Sabbath dayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to be vſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in each reformed family.</note> to examine all your Family in thoſe things which are euery day taught them on the Sabbath by your Miniſter, who is a godly, learned, and a zealous Preacher: and examine them ſo, that you may know how eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one doth marke and remember,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6457:21"/> what things were taught, and how they were confirmed and applied. <note n="e" place="margin">The careleſnes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, of luke-warm Laodice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts at large, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in this our age, and are euen glutted with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> Many men are exceeding careleſſe herein, for where almoſt is one among many, that queſtioneth with his ſeruants, about Religion at all? It may be, ſometimes (ſaith one) that they will ſend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Church: but when they returne, what doe they aſke them of their learning or profiting there? vnleſſe perhaps once at the hundreds end, hée vouchſafe to know the Chapter, and the Verſe of the Text, (which betwixt the Church doore &amp; home,) euen a Parrot would be taught to pronounce. Let ſuch ſend any of their people vpon ſome worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and they will be ſure to aske his ſeruant how hee ſped, and nothing will he leaue vnasked to vnderſtand the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the arrand hee ſent him about: but for Gods buſineſſe, and Soule mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, be they performed negligently, or not done at all, it mattereth not.</p>
                  <p>And almoſt all men doe now content <note place="margin">Note this.</note> themſelues with a flight examination; hence is it, that their ſonnes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants can neither ſhew the ſumme and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6457:21"/> diuiſion of the Text, nor what doctrines were drawne from it, much leſſe how they were confimed and in the vſe appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but onely they bring certaine words, and ſentences, or ſimilitudes, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the purpoſe whereto any thing was ſpoken by the Preacher. I <note place="margin">Note this.</note> would wiſh you therefore, I ſay, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your Children and ſeruants with ſuch diligent care, that you may know how euery one doth marke and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what things were taught, and how euery doctrine was confirmed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, and where any one faileth, let the next that ſtandeth in order by him, ſhew and teach him: &amp; when all haue brought out their ſtore, and ſhewed their beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to make repetition, then you your ſelfe are alſo to helpe them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by a diligent repetition, confirming and applying to your whole Familie (and to your owne heart and affections) <note place="margin">Note this.</note> all the doctrines that were deliuered: which I would wiſh you to doe with all Godly zeale and feruencie, forthwith and immediatly after your comming from Church, before you receiue your bodily foode.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6457:22"/>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVHere that courſe is continued,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>men are commonly accounted Puritans, and we that haue vſed it, haue beene much derided, ſcorned, and moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for it, and many men (you know) in the Countrey, doe call it and terme it a priuate Preaching, and do not ceaſe to ſay, that therein wee ſhew our ſelues to bee more preciſe then wiſe: what ſay you of ſuch ſcorners?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>FIrſt I ſay, that though ſuch eſtéeme <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> wiſedome it ſelfe to bee but fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and folly: yet are they themſelues the onely fooles by Gods account; <hi>Who ſcorneth the ſcorner, Pro.</hi> 3. 34. and ſaith, that fooles deſpiſe wiſedome and inſtruction, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. 7.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, I ſay therefore, that ſuch <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as would bee wiſe, muſt not ſit in the ſeate of ſcorners, nor be daunted with ſuch ſcorning, though it bee a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6457:22"/> 
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 36.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, becauſe ſuch men account <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> this courſe to be a nouelty, and ſeeme to yeeld much vnto <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> I would wiſh them to conſider well Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens</hi> cenſure, who ſaith; <hi>That euery</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Paterfami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onator eſt in domo ſua, iuxta Auguſtini ſententiam dicentis; quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioator eſt in ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtu, hoc quilibet pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfamilias in domo ſua.</note> 
                     <hi>Houſeholder ſhould bee the ſame in his owne houſe, as the Preacher is in the Pulpit, or in Gods houſe:</hi> That is, that hée ſhould diligently teach and inſtruct his houſhold, as <hi>Abraham did,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his houſhold to doe iuſtice and iudgement, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 19. And as the Mother of <hi>Lemuel</hi> did, <hi>Pro.</hi> 31 2. 3. who by their ſedulitie and earneſtneſſe in teaching, did ſet as it were, an edge vpon their doctrine, in applying it to the affections of their hearers, that it might moue much their minds, &amp; pierce deepe into their hard and ſtonie hearts. Now the ſame that they did, you and euery Houſeholder is commanded to do, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6. 7. where the Hebrew reading is; <hi>Thou ſhalt whet theſe words on thy Children:</hi> and agreeable thereto is that, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 24. 25. <hi>Let vs whet one another,</hi> as it is in the Greeke: pointing at, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6457:23"/> noting, by that metaphor of <hi>Whetting,</hi> our ſpirituall dulneſſe, which like blunt tooles, haue need to be whetted by day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teaching and admoniſhing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Perceiue by the former places, that</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>ſuch as are Parents and gouernors of Families, ſhould not be like Luke-warme Laodiceans, whom the Lord Ieſus willeth to repent, Reuel.</hi> 3. 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. <hi>For none indeed doe truely repent till they be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, (ſaith one) for feruencie or zeale is an effect of true repentance,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 11. <hi>I perceiue alſo by the former pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>that not onely minſters, but alſo all Chriſtians ſhould be zealous, according to that general precept: Be feruent in Spirit, ſeruing the LORD, Rom.</hi> 12. 11. <hi>And that therefore they ſhould ſet an edge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their admonitions and inſtructions,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>is not that your meaning, ſir?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6457:23"/>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>YEs aſſuredly, for it is the very life of good doctrine, to moue affection much, beeing well applyed, without which, it is but like a plaſter kept in a pocket, and not applied to the place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. <note place="margin">A Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SIth then, in teaching, it is ſo needfull to moue affection, ſhew me (I pray you) ſome helpes and meanes, to make my houſhold admonitions and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions powerfull, to worke vpon the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of my Family.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>TWo things are needfull in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to mooue affection much: Firſt feruency; Secondly, conſtancy: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Teach therfore and inſtruct your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with feeling and with feruency; in particular, in reprouing ſuch as are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6457:24"/> and preſumptuous, do it not as ſome do, with a ſmiling countenance: but as our Sauiour did with an angrie countenance, mourning alſo, as he did, for the hardneſſe of their hearts. <hi>Marke</hi> 3. 5.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in admoniſhing the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Charge &amp; command</hi> them to deale religiouſly, iuſtly and truly, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, in comforting the féeble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and when any matter of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is to bee applied, ſpeake then with chéereful ſpéech and countenance, if you can: for God requireth mercy to bee ſhewed with chéerefulneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8. and he loueth a chéerefull giuer, (chiefly in giuing ſpirituall gifts:) be not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in comforting, drowſie, heauy-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and leaden like: but ſhewe your ſelfe in comforting, comfortable, and to be comforted. Thus much concerning feruency.</p>
                  <p>Againe, to make your inſtruction powerfull, you muſt teach and admoniſh conſtantly and diligently: for as the drops of raine cannot weare thorow an
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6457:24"/> hard ſtone, without often dropping, how ſharpe ſoeuer the water, or the dropping be: ſo the Word applyed not often, but ſeldome earneſtly, will not pierce thorow the ſtony heart of man; though doctrine well applied bee as the dropping of the raine vpon the ſtone, or earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 2. which muſt haue, to <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 2</note> make it fruitfull, both the early and the latter raine.</p>
                  <p>The heart of man is more hard then the Adamant ſtone, and yet by often beating vpon it, by the hammer of Gods Lawe, it may bee bruiſed and humbled, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 29. The powerfull applying of <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 29.</note> doctrine is as the nailes, which vnleſſe they bee with many blowes hammered and beaten vp throughly vnto the head, will not holde a ſtrong and thicke ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 12. 11. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the effectuall applying of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is like vnto the grindſtone or whetſtone, which will not without much grinding &amp; often whetting make edge-tooles (beeing much and often dulled) fit to worke withall, or kéene to cut: So our hearts and affections
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6457:25"/> being hardened, blunted, and dulled by the deceitfulneſſe of ſinne, had need to be much whetted, that they may bée made fit for Gods worke, by daily and earneſt admonition and exhortation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 24. 25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 13.</p>
                  <p>Therfore <hi>Moſes</hi> in the foreſayd place ſheweth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6. 7. That wee muſt <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 6. 7.</note> make our admonitions powerfull to pierce: firſt, by hauing and feeling the power thereof abiding and working in our owne harts, and then next in whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame vpon our children and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by continuall talking and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſacred Scriptures: when we walke in the way, when we lye downe, and when we riſe vp. Laſtly, if you doe deſire to teach and inſtruct your family ſo, that you may moue much &amp; through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke vpon the hearts of your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, euen all good and holy affections: Conſider then alſo of other needefull helpes thereunto belonging: namely, that in your family you muſt walk wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">Adiuncts to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer means</note> prayſe orderly, reward worthily, and correct accordingly.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="conference">
               <pb facs="tcp:6457:25"/>
               <head>THE THIRD CONFE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, concerning the foure laſt mentioned helps and meanes to make Houſehold inſtruction powerfull, to worke good and holy affections in the HEARERS.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>SONNE.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>EXplaine and confirme, I pray you, in particular, theſe former dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FATHER.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                     </label> FIrſt, as God commandeth, you muſt walke wiſely, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 4. 5. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. 15. ſhunne therefore all groſſe and open vices, otherwiſe that which you build with the one hand, you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6457:26"/> pull downe with the other, and are in Gods account a murtherer, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 11. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 15.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, walke wiſely, in all good waies, that ſo doing, you may adorne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of our Sauiour in all things, <hi>Titus</hi> 2. 10. In particular, pray hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 10</note> and dayly for (and with) your Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and in ſpeciall, for euery one, vpon all occaſions as <hi>Iob</hi> did, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1. 4. 5.</p>
                  <p>Next, looke and prye vpon euery Weeke day, into their carriage; and on the Lords day, ſée that euery one from Sabbath to Sabbath, do diligently fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the publike miniſterie, and how they profit in knowledge, and grow in Grace, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, you ſhould praiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> your Child, your ſon, your daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, your Seruant, when they doe any thing well, laudably, or praiſe-worthy; for praiſe is a ſpur to quicken, &amp; incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in all good courſes, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 6. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2. 3. 6. 13. 19. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3. 8.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, reward them when they do <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> well; for a <hi>Reward is as a precious ſtone, ſaith Salomon, it proſpereth whitherſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:6457:26"/> 
                     <hi>it turneth, Pro.</hi> 17. 8. That is, as one expounds it, a gift or reward hath great force to gaine the hearts of them to whomſoeuer it is giuen.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, correct them alſo, when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> they doe euill: correction muſt bee vſed when any will not be amended by admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; if after due and many admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, you giue not meete correction; then doe you honour your ſonnes aboue the Lord, as <hi>Elye</hi> did, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 19. yea though for a fit you do earneſtly reproue them with <hi>Elye,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 23. 24. 25. His cockering of his Children, brought deſtruction vpon him and his, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall calamitie (as you know) to the Church of God, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 10. 11. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Yet <note n="h" place="margin">Careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting.</note> many careleſſe <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> like luke-warme <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> neuer cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their vnreformed Familie, for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honouring God by ſwearing, Sabbath-breaking, or for other faults againſt the firſt Table, but onely in ſuch caſes as concerne their owne perſons, their own credit, profit, pleaſure, &amp;c. But, let all ſuch know, that not correcting ſuch foule offences, they draw on themſelues
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6457:27"/> and others all common calamities, as <hi>Elye</hi> did, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 10. 11. 18. 19. 20. Correct therefore your vnreformed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, if you deſire to free your ſelfe &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feareful &amp; grieuous iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: <note place="margin">The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting children &amp; ſeruants.</note> And correct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in this order &amp; manner:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, after due monition, conuincing, if poſſibly it may be, their conſciences; otherwiſe they will waxe worſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more obdurate, ſtubborn &amp; ſubtill.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, correct after anger, not in anger, and in paſſion; for anger oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times can kéepe no meaſure. <hi>Anger,</hi> ſaid a Philoſopher, is a ſhort <hi>madneſſe:</hi> and therefore when <hi>Tarentinus</hi> was to correct his ſeruant, hee ſayd: <hi>I would beat thee, but that I am angry with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, correct alſo chiefly &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for the breach of the firſt foure Commandements.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, correct not with too much lenitie; for too much lenity cauſeth (as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> one ſaith) ſecuritie: ſo too much ſecurity prouoketh to wrath and to deſperate ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: ſeuerity ſhould be ſhunned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 4.</note> And therefore, ſayth one, Correct not, nor beate not thy ſeruants with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6457:27"/> ſtaues, as if they were dogges, nor with too many ſtripes, as if they were bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaues: but kéepe alway an euen hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two extremes: and when thou correcteſt, be thou humbled to God; conſidering in them, thine owne natural <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1.</note> or occaſionall corruption, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, delay not correction too long, left they grow ſturdy and incorrigible, <hi>Eccleſiaſtic.</hi> 30. 8. 12. <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 13. 24. <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 23. 13. 14. <hi>Prouerbs.</hi> 19. 18. &amp; leſt any roote of bitternes ſpring vp, and therby many be defiled, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 15. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixt and laſtly: if priuate correction in the Family reforme them not; bring them (if their vices be openly nocious and ſcandalous to many,) before the Magiſtrate; or Church-gouernors, to be openly corrected, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. 21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 21 <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 17 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5.</note> 18. 17. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 5. And if neither pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate nor publike correction worke vpon them, to their reformation; expell them, and rid thy houſe and Familie of them, as <hi>Dauids</hi> example ſhould direct thee to doe, vpon that occaſion, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 101. 7. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 7</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Prayer vttered by R. R. Miniſter, and Preacher of Gods Word, in time of his ſickneſſe: Penned for a remembrance, &amp;c.</hi> (<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Moſt glorious &amp; moſt gracious God, who <hi>killeſt and makeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue: bringeſt downe to the graue, and rayſeſt vp againe:</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 6.</note> who v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt ſickneſſe as <hi>thy Sargeant,</hi> thereby areſting vs, to renue our reckoning with thee, and our conuerſion. <note n="b" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 31. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. 3.</note> There is no health in my fleſh, O Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy diſpleaſure: nor any reſt in my bones, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 38. 3</note> by reaſon of my ſinne: I haue deſerued a double death, both tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and eternall, by originall and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſin: <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 23 <hi>&amp; Deu</hi> 27. 26.</note> O that I could chatter like a Crane, and mourne like a Doue, <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 38. 12.</note> as <hi>Ezekias</hi> did. Graunt mee (O my God) to mourne and ſorrow more for my ſins, then for my ſickneſſe, for through my ſinnes, thy Goſpell hath beene blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:6457:28"/> thy glorie impaired, thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit grieued, good men offended, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill men emboldned. O gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, forgiue me, &amp; grant vnto me, both pardon of my ſins, and power againſt my ſinnes: <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 19. 12, 13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 12, 13.</note> O ſubdue ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſpeedily: thou haſt promiſed to tread Satan ſhortly vnder all our feete. <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 16. 20</note>
            </p>
            <p>Raigne thou wholly ouer vs, and ſuffer Satan no longer to ſubdue vs, to <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. 10 <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23. 24.</note> captiuate or to impriſon vs: Break off his bolts, hale mee from his holt: draw me from his dungeon. <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>cant.</hi> 1. 3.</note> O draw me vnto thee and wee will runne after thee: Father of Heauen heare me, and make ſpeed to helpe me. O grant me grace, henceforward (if I liue) alwaies to adorne <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 10.</note> thy glorious Goſpell, that heretofore I haue blemiſhed, to <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 13</note> aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thy glorie that in time paſt I haue impayred: to cheere <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Re.</hi> 3. 20 <hi>cant.</hi> 4. 10. 11.</note> vp thy Spirit, that heretofore I haue grieued <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 30. <hi>cant.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Eſay</hi> 7. 13. <hi>Eſa</hi> 7. 13.</note>: To glad the godly, whom heretofore I haue made heauie-hearted, <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 136. 139 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 7. 8.</note> and to reclaime others from euill, which heretofore I haue emboldned vnto euill. <note n="p" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 21. <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 1. 2. <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 42.</note> And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch (O gracious Father) as thou
<pb facs="tcp:6457:29"/> haſt promiſed to ſtrengthen vs vpon our bed of ſorrowes: yea to pillow vs vp, and to make all our bed in our ſicknes, <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 3</note> and that thou wilt ſend thy good Angel to deliuer vs, when no hand can helpe vs <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34. 7.</note>: O therefore performe this thy ſweet and gracious promiſe: Let now thy power appeare in my weakneſſe: <note n="ſ" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9.</note> to the praiſe of thy rich <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 4.</note> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: in Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: euen ſo be it, euen ſo, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL.</hi> 5. 13.</bibl> 
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prayſe, and honour, and glorie, and power, bee vnto him that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lambe for euermore. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6457:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
